so let's discuss the performance of
multi trading and how can it be better
than simply running things one at a time
so if we have a processor with no
multi-threading support then this is how
two threads might run these are Cycles
going in this direction so each Notch
here is a cycle and we have four
instructions that can execute in this
cycle so this is what might happen a
green thread might be using this and
this slot in this cycle and the other
two issue slots are not used because the
processor has no ready instructions to
dis patch to execution in this cycle
let's say there is a data dependence so
next Cycle One instruction can wake up
and then let's say that in the next
cycle we can have three instructions go
but then let's say that all of the
instructions are now waiting for
something to happen so let's say for a
few Cycles we don't get much happening
then when it happens we get to execute
let's say all four
and then maybe another cycle with two
Etc so things can be like this basically
much of the time we are running with a
less than fully utilized processor
pipeline let's say that at this point we
get an interrupt and because there is
another thread that is ready to run we
now get many cycles of the operating
system doing its thing so it's also
going to utilize the pipeline in some
way but it spends many cycles basically
figuring out which thread to run next
eventually decides that it's going to be
the blue thread and begins executing
instructions from that thread on the
processor so this is where we return
from the inup and start executing a new
thread because let's say we have these
two threads ready to go so the blue
thread in a similar way will be using
the processor partially let's say it has
a level one miss takes a while to get
the thing from level two meanwhile maybe
it's able to do something for a while
but eventually runs out of things to do
and then for example starts doing
something again and let's say this whole
cycle is used so this is what might
happen in a processor with no multi-
threading support in that case really
the overhead that you created by having
to switch between threads is probably
larger than the gains we are getting
from running them we were better off
just running a single thread that does
the work of both of these threads so
really a single procer with no multi-
threading is capable of doing this with
a good operating system not because it's
better for performance to break work
into multiple threads but because we
want to be able to simultaneously run
several applications and make progress
in them so that for example if you're
playing games and playing music at the
same time we alternate between the game
and the music player fast enough for you
to not be able to tell that they're
really executing one at a time on your
One Core
if we have a chip multiprocessor we get
to do something like this now we have
two cores Each of which pretty much gets
to execute one thread so it's faster of
course than this and we can benefit
truly from being able to write multi-
threaded programs but you have to have
two cores for it so the cost is about
twice the cost of a single core here so
with fine grain multi- trading what we
have is really One Core but with
separate sets of registers for these
threads and some scheduling logic with
fine grain multi threading every cycle
we can switch between threads so what
happens is the green thread gets exactly
the same behavior in the first cycle in
the second cycle we do the blue thread
so we get the behavior of its first
cycle here then we do some of the work
from the green thread again then from
the blue thread third cycle of the green
thread third cycle of the blue thread
and now we would be running the green
thread except that there is nothing to
run there but what happens is the blue
thread has something to do so we spend
another cycle on the blue thread and
then the green thread is still somewhere
here there is nothing ready to run but
these operations are going on so the
blue thread gets one more cycle here at
this point the blue thread has nothing
to do but the green one now has
something to do so we end up doing the
work of the green thread and then for
another cycle then let's say neither of
the threads can do something but then
the blue thread is able to do this
because it's been three Cycles since
here and then again and as you can see
we get done faster than here because we
are able to eliminate some of the Cycles
where we were not able to do anything so
fine grain multi trading benefits from
the fact that when there is a long
period of idleness in one thread for
example due to a cache miss you might be
able to run still instructions from the
other thread and finally let's see what
happens in smt in smt we are able to mix
instructions from different threads in
the same cycle so what we will get is
the green one gets this the blue one
also wants to use the bottom slot and
let's say that there is a unit there for
example the load unit that you have to
use here but we can still run this in
the same cycle next cycle the green
thread does this the blue one wants to
now do this this and this and we can
let's say do these two but let's say
there is a dependence from this to this
so we can only do this one next cycle
the green thread can do this and from
the blue thread we can maybe do this
instruction or maybe not so let's say we
can't because maybe this one depends
also on the one that we haven't done or
the next one now however there is some
period of idleness in the green thread
and now the blue thread gets to make up
for missing out on some things so it's
able to maybe do this and this dependent
instruction and at this point the green
thread is ready to run something so we
can choose whether to run the green or
the blue one let's say that the green
thread has a higher priority so we
always try to do instructions from the
green thread and only fill the gaps with
the blue ones now we've done this next
cycle we still do whatever we can from
the green thread We Now can do this and
now we only have the blue thread left to
do if the green thread has more stuff to
do we can do this so as you can see with
smt we get to populate unused
slots in what would otherwise be a full
speed execution of the green thread so
that the blue thread gets to make
progress while the green thread really
is not suffering from it and we can do
that for more than just two threads so
for example if if we had four threads we
might be able to actually do another
thread at a slightly slower pace and
blue while we are also doing this so
with smt what we doing we're really
using underutilized issue slots in our
outof order supercal processor the
hardware cost to do this is very small
our fetch stage needs to be slightly
more complicated to allow us to fetch
from one or the other PC and our
register file needs to be slightly more
complicated because really there are now
two sets of architectural registers but
other than that the whole comp
complicated outof order engine stays the
same so let's say this is going to cost
something like 5% of the cost of a no
multi threaded processor this here again
after we do register renaming and
everything else the processor scheduler
stays just the same we just need to put
instructions from multiple threads in
the instruction window so that they
could be scheduled from there and now
also when we commit we have to figure
out which instruction belongs to which
commit and so on so the cost is slightly
larger than fine grain but still not
very large because again most of the
complicated reservation stations and
execution units and everything else
stays pretty much unmodified so this is
going to have performance that is maybe
very close to a
CMP two threads here two threads here
maybe making almost as much progress but
at a very small fraction of this cost